Zach Hafen-Saavedra

PhD, Computational & Theoretical Astrophysics z.hafen.saavedra@gmail.com || zhafen.github.io || Chicago, IL || 😱 🛅

Summary

[click here for a work sample]

Always-growing scientist with over 10 years of experience analyzing relational data in Python. I lead solution development and draw on my extensive science-communication experience to deliver audience-tailored products. Seeking positions in data science and related fields.

Skills

Techniques: data analysis (inc. cleaning, visualization, time-series), machine learning (inc. NLP), Bayesian statistics, containerization, dashboarding, code testing/CI, GIS (inc. image registration), computer vision **Interpersonal skills:** technical leadership and management, storytelling, mentoring **Tools:** Python (inc. numpy, pandas, matplotlib, scikit-learn, pytorch, nltk), C/C++, PostgreSQL (inc. PostGIS), NoSQL, Docker, BI (Cognos BI, Streamlit), parallel computing, GDAL, OpenCV, git, Windows/Mac/Unix

Experience

Far Horizons Data Scientist Adler Planetarium

September 2023 - Present Chicago, IL

As a museum resident expert, worked with youth engagement staff to effectively communicate complex

- concepts, including providing deep-impact education to 20+ high-school students and 4 interns.

 Developed an automated ETL and image-registration pipeline using Python and shell scripting, dramatically
- increasing the georeferencing speed from 4 manual images/hour to 5000 images/hour.

 Applied computer-vision feature matching techniques to precisely georeference aerial images, constraining
- the position to within 10 pixels, down from 1000 pixels.
- Streamlined pipeline accessibility by containerizing with Docker and creating a well-documented intuitive UI, reducing the training requirement to under 10 minutes for non-experts.
- Utilized CodeBuild to deploy a Docker-containerized pipeline on AWS and host the artifacts on S3, giving users easy access to the output PostgreSQL DB.
- Produced a high-quality night map of Indianapolis to assess the effects of light pollution on urban wildlife.
- Directed the adoption of Agile project management, facilitating majority-community-driven development.
- Trained a convolutional neural network to interpret cat vocalizations, achieving 90% validation accuracy and earning a merit of distinction in the Erdos Institute Data Science program.

Business Data Analyst

June 2023 - September 2023

Northwestern University, Center for Interdisc. Explor. and Research in Astrophysics

Evanston, IL

- Created a web-based BI dashboard using Streamlit, enabling business staff to analyze data and present updated, tailored visualizations to stakeholders.
- Adopted a low-dependency shell-scripting+Python solution stack tailored to organization resources, guaranteeing operational continuity and maintainability of solutions.
- Updated reporting to use enterprise Cognos BI, restoring access to crucial financial information.
- Automated data extraction from PDFs and visualized key insights, guiding leadership in forming datadriven action plans for improving diversity, equity, and inclusion.

McCue Prize Postdoctoral Fellow in Cosmology

July 2020 - June 2023

University of California-Irvine, Department of Physics and Astronomy

Irvine, CA

- Developed a Python-frontend, C++-backend code to evaluate metrics derived from NLP document embeddings, and presented at Al4Science on a metric correlating with a 150% increase in citations.
- Automated data retrieval from NASA APIs, extracting metadata for more than a million papers.

- Utilized scikit-learn and PyTorch to construct an ensemble voting model for paper impact, with a citation count validation RMSE 2/3 of the baseline error.
- Orchestrated a mock data challenge spanning nine international institutions, quantifying the domain of validity for stastical models of intergalactic gas.
- · Interfaced mock data software with an open-source spectra database, decreasing uncertainty by half.
- Organized a workshop of twenty leading galaxy-formation experts, popularizing a new paradigm for the formation of our Milky Way.
- Used national supercomputers to process 20+ TB of relational data, pinpointing causal phenomena behind our galaxy's disk-like structure.
- Built a combined framework of black hole, star cluster, and galaxy simulations to predict the origin of anomalous gravitational waves detected by LIGO.

National Science Foundation Graduate Fellow in K-12 Education Northwestern University, Department of Physics and Astronomy

June 2014 - July 2020 Evanston, IL

- Employed software-development best practices such as version control, code review, testing, and CI to develop 13+ open-source packages and contribute to 6 more.
- Crafted award-winning visualizations displayed throughout Chicago, effectively communicating complex scientific results to the public.
- Partnered with schools to pioneer a high-school data science program, reaching over 100 underrepresented students and paving the way for future work on data literacy.
- Performed time-series decision-tree classification to predict the cosmic origins of the atoms we are made of, suggesting an extragalactic origin for 1/3 of our solar system.
- Modified C code and ran 100,000+ CPU-hour simulations to increase the statistical power and realism of theoretical estimates, generating data used by 30+ researchers.
- Founded the Physics Graduate Student Council to improve student life, retention, and recruitement, tied to a nearly 200% increase in recruitement.
- Collaborated with 100+ researchers, leading to 36 published papers, 7 as lead author.

Education

The Erdős Institute
Data Science Certificate
Irvine, CA

Northwestern University
PhD, MS, Physics and Astronomy
Specialization: Astrophysical Data Analysis

University of Northern Colorado
BS, Mathematical Physics

2020

2014

Greeley, CO

Core Values

- · Growth, to keep changing and growing
- Accuracy, to be accurate in my opinions and beliefs
- Rationality, to be guided by reason and logic
- Purpose, to have meaning and direction in my life
- Passion, to have deep feelings about ideas, activities, or people
- Openness, to be open to new experiences, ideas, and options
- Compassion, to feel and act on concern for others
- Honesty, to be honest and truthful
- Responsibility, to make and carry out responsible decisions
- Faithfulness, to be in loyal and true relationships